{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "By defeating Eugenius at one of these locations in 394, Theodosius I quashed polytheism in favor of Christianity and briefly reunified the Roman Empire. Before a battle at another one of these geographical locations, the winning commander saw the phrase “in hoc signo vinces” in a dream, after which he painted the Chi-Rho [kye-roh] on his soldiers” shields. Constantine I defeated Maxentius in a 312 AD battle at, for ten points, what type of geographical location, an Italian one of which is crossed by the Milvian Bridge?",
      "answer": [
        "rivers",
        "bridge before read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The phrase “Sherman pledge” is derived from William Sherman’s refusal to run in this election year. A candidate in this election year was tarnished by Samuel Burchard’s comment that his party was becoming that of “rum, Romanism, and rebellion.” The victor in this election year was taunted with the phrase “Ma, Ma, where’s my Pa?” This election year was the first won by a Democrat since the Civil War. James G. Blaine lost in, for ten points, what election year in which Grover Cleveland was first elected President?",
      "answer": "US presidential election of 1884"
    },
    {
      "question": "This novel was composed during the volcanic winter after the eruption of Mount Tambora, which may have inspired the setting of a frame story in which Robert Walton meets the protagonist while exploring the North Pole. In this novel, Elizabeth Lavenza is killed on her wedding night after her husband refuses to create a female companion for his first creation. For ten points, name this novel about Victor, a mad scientist who creates life, written by Mary Shelley.",
      "answer": [
        "Frankenstein",
        "or, The Modern Prometheus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During the trial for this event, Max Steur made Kate Alterman constantly repeat her story, and then accused her of memorizing the facts when she did so. Max Blanck and Isaac Harris were arrested for manslaughter due to this event. During this event, doors to the stairways in the Asch Building were locked to prevent unauthorized breaks. For ten points, name this 1911 disaster in which dozens of garment workers died in a Manhattan fire.",
      "answer": "Triangle Shirtwaist Factory fire"
    },
    {
      "question": "This field’s “new” form combines it with ethnography and was developed by Lewis Binford. In a book that defined this field’s “processual” form, Willey and Phillips claimed that it is “anthropology or it is nothing.” The Harris Matrix outlines four “laws” of this field, including the law of stratigraphic succession and the law of superposition. Practitioners of this field study sites like Skara Brae and Tel Megiddo. For ten points, name this field of study that examines artifacts and past human societies.",
      "answer": "archaeology"
    },
    {
      "question": "This policy was enacted under the leadership of D.F. Mala and his National Party. In accordance with this policy, the movement of citizens were restricted by the Pass Laws. People protesting this policy were massacred at Sharpeville and Soweto. In 1993, F.W. de Klerk shared a Nobel Peace Prize for helping to end this policy. Nelson Mandela opposed, for ten points, what South African system of racial segregation?",
      "answer": "apartheid"
    },
    {
      "question": "Using the method of interpretatio romana, Tacitus identified this god with Mercury in his Germania. Oneceremonytothisgodinvolvedhanginghorses.Thisgod,whowashungfromtheWorldTree,sacrificed his eye for wisdom. This husband of Frigga rides the eight-legged horse Sleipnir and is the father of Balder and Thor. This god’s German form is the namesake of Wednesday. For ten points, name this chief god of the Norse pantheon.",
      "answer": [
        "Odin",
        "Wodan",
        "Wuotan"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This event was a consolation choice after proposals for it to be held at Egyptian pyramids, a Roman amphitheater in Tunisia at sunrise, or a cruise ship fell through. Michael Lindsay-Hogg filmed this event, which took place at 3 Savile Row and featured Billy Preston. This event, which included multiple takes of “Don’t Let Me Down” and “Get Back,” was interrupted by police responding to noise complaints. The album Let It Be features songs recorded during, for ten points, what impromptu January 1969 event above London, the last time the Fab Four played live?",
      "answer": "the Beatles” rooftop concert"
    },
    {
      "question": "The United States organized the “coalition of the willing” against this country after a report by an informant known as “Curveball.” A photograph of a man in this country wearing a hood and standing on a box was used as proof that American soldiers were abusing prisoners in Abu Ghraib. In 2003, the United States invaded this country to secure non-existent weapons of mass destruction. For ten points, name this country that was led by Saddam Hussein from Baghdad.",
      "answer": [
        "Iraq",
        "the Iraqi Republic"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This monarch introduced religious freedom in his kingdom with the Declaration of Indulgence, which was partially meant to protect his own Catholicism. George Jeffreys was appointed by this man to severely punish the instigators of the Monmouth Rebellion in the Bloody Assizes. This successor of Charles II served as the Stuart king before being replaced by the House of Orange. For ten points, name this King of England overthrown in the Glorious Revolution.",
      "answer": [
        "James II of England",
        "James VI of Scotland"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The McCone Commission investigated violence in this city, concluding that high unemployment and poor education led to a 1965 riot. Police in this city were accused of “kicking a pregnant woman” while arresting Marquette Frye and his family. In 1992, riots broke out in this city after four police officers were acquitted of beating an unarmed black man. The Watts and Rodney King Riots took place in, for ten points, what largest city in California?",
        "answer": [
          "Los Angeles",
          "LA"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1943, soldiers stationed in Los Angeles clashed with Mexican-American youth in this race-fueled riot.",
        "answer": "Zoot Suit Riot"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Treaty of Utrecht allowed this organization to build a depot in the English town of Lynn. The Victual Brothers temporarily seized a city dominated by this city in modern Gotland, the port of Visby. The Kingdom of Sweden weakened this organization by capturing ports in Pomerania and Prussia. For ten points, name this maritime league, largely made up of German city-states, that controlled Medieval Baltic trade.",
        "answer": "Hanseatic League"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the most influential cities in the Hanseatic League was this free imperial city on the River Elbe.",
        "answer": "Hamburg"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This state’s national guard once joined forces with this state’s Fuel and Iron Company to attack a group of striking coal miners in what became known as the Ludlow Massacre. This state was home to the 59ers Gold Rush, which centered around Pike’s Peak and fueled the growth of cities like Boulder and its capital, a “Mile High” city. For ten points, name this western US state where miners built the city of Denver.",
        "answer": "Colorado"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This US President vetoed Colorado’s initial push for statehood, citing its low population. Nebraska became a state during this man’s administration, helping pass the 14th Amendment over this man’s objection.",
        "answer": "Andrew Johnson"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The indigenous population of this nation killed and ate 70 European settlers during the Boyd Massacre after a chief was whipped on the namesake ship. The Native Land Court ended the communal land system in this country, the site of early 19th century intertribal conflicts called the Musket Wars. The British signed the Treaty of Waitangi with the native people of, for ten points, what country in Oceania settled by the Maori?",
        "answer": "New Zealand"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Maori fought a short conflict with the British over a tax on this animal. A type of this animal named the Lhasa Apso protected temples in Tibet.",
        "answer": "Dog War"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country threatened to build the Salwa Canal, which would turn its neighbor’s territory from a peninsula into an island. Over 700 people died in the Mina Stampede in this nation in 2015 while approaching Jamarat Bridge. An attack on this country’s Abqaiq Oil Field, once thought to be the work of Houthi rebels, was instead proven to be an Iranian attack in September 2019. King Salman and Crown Prince Mohammad bin Salman lead, for ten points, what Middle Eastern country with capital Riyadh?",
        "answer": "Saudi Arabia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In October 2018, Saudi Arabian agents murdered this dissident journalist in the Saudi consulate in Turkey.",
        "answer": "Jamal Khashoggi"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The 4th book of the Continuations of the Chronicle of Fredegar gives a biased account of this battle. This battle occurred after Odo the Great suffered multiple defeats at Narbonne and Bordeaux, leading his army to combine with Frankish forces. One side at this battle had no cavalry, opting to form the phalanx formation to combat Abd al-Rahman al-Ghafiqi’s horses. For ten points, name this victory by Charles Martel that turned back the Muslim invasion of Europe.",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Tours",
          "Battle of Poitier"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Odo the Great, who had earlier fought the Umayyads at the Battle of Toulouse, was duke of this French region",
        "answer": "Aquitaine"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This politician responded to Harold Stassen’s calls to ban the Communist Party by saying “You can’t shoot an idea with a gun” in the first Presidential debate to be broadcast on the radio. This politician prosecuted mob boss Lucky Luciano as a Special Prosecutor for Fiorello La Guardia before being elected Governor of New York in 1943. A photograph shows an opponent of this politician triumphantly holding a copy of the Chicago Daily Tribune. For ten points, name this politician who did not actually defeat Truman in the 1948 Presidential election.",
        "answer": "Thomas Edmund Dewey"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "While serving as Manhattan District Attorney, Dewey prosecuted several corrupt members of this institution. Previous Presidential hopeful Samuel J. Tilden rose to fame after investigating this institution.",
        "answer": "Tammany Hall"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A portrait of this man by Ingres [ahng] shows him seated on a throne while wearing a golden laurel. Jacques-Louis David [dah-VEED] painted numerous portraits of this man, including one at his study in the Tuileries [twee-luh-ree] Palace and another in which this man rides a rearing gray horse while crossing the Alps. For ten points, name this French Emperor who was painted leading troops at the Battle of Waterloo.",
        "answer": "Napoleon Bonaparte or Napoleon I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The bottom left corner of David’s Napoleon Crossing the Alps includes the names of three famous generals inscribed on rocks. One is Bonaparte; name either of the other men.",
        "answer": [
          "Hannibal Barca and/or Charlemagne",
          "Carolus Magnus"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Henry Ford",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Largest city in Michigan, where he started his company.",
          "answer": "Detroit"
        },
        {
          "question": "Car, nicknamed the Tin Lizzie, that put his company on the map.",
          "answer": "Model T"
        },
        {
          "question": "Production method he championed in which parts moved along a belt to be put together.",
          "answer": "assembly line"
        },
        {
          "question": "Daily wage he paid to his workers starting in 1914, a revolutionary amount.",
          "answer": "five dollars per day"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where he established Fordlandia, a failed rubber plantation.",
          "answer": "Brazil"
        },
        {
          "question": "UAW union leader from 1946 to 1970 who feuded with Ford and fought at the “Battle of the Overpass.”",
          "answer": "Walter Reuther"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where Ford built the River Rouge plant; it also names a newspaper edited by Ford.",
          "answer": [
            "Dearborn",
            "Dearborn Independent"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Antisemitic series of pamphlets he wrote, subtitled “The World’s Problem.”",
          "answer": "The International Jew"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Black Death",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Disease caused by Yersinia pestis that is blamed for the Black Death.",
          "answer": "Bubonic plague or black plague"
        },
        {
          "question": "Animals that spread the disease while being attached to black rats.",
          "answer": "fleas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ancient trade route between China and Europe that helped spread the disease.",
          "answer": "Silk Road or Silk Route"
        },
        {
          "question": "Occupation that dealt with the plague while wearing a heavy overcoat and a beak mask.",
          "answer": "plague doctors"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nomadic ethnic group originating in northern India that was blamed for the outbreak and discriminated against.",
          "answer": [
            "Romani people",
            "gypsy, but inform the players that it’s considered a pejorative term"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Empire, led by Jani Beg, that may have started the outbreak by launching corpses into Kaffa.",
          "answer": [
            "Mongol Empire",
            "Golden Horde"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Survey ordered by William the Conqueror that gives the closest pre-Black Death population of England.",
          "answer": "Domesday Book"
        },
        {
          "question": "1351 law created by Edward III to address the labor shortage caused by the plague.",
          "answer": "Statute of Laborers"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Chiang Kai-Shek",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Rival political party that took power in China after he was forced out of the country.",
          "answer": "Communist Party"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island to which he fled after the Chinese Civil War.",
          "answer": [
            "Taiwan",
            "Formosa"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "River, the second-longest in China, he had flooded to slow down invading Japanese forces.",
          "answer": "Yellow River"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political party he led, often called the Nationalists.",
          "answer": [
            "Kuomintang",
            "KMT"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who mentored him and put him in charge of the Whampoa Military Academy.",
          "answer": "Sun Yat-Sen"
        },
        {
          "question": "1937 incident at a bridge near Beijing that forced Chiang into the second Sino-Japanese War.",
          "answer": "Marco Polo Bridge Incident"
        },
        {
          "question": "1936 incident in which he was kidnapped and forced to create a United Front.",
          "answer": "Xi’an Incident"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wife of Chiang Kai-shek and youngest of the influential Soong sisters.",
          "answer": "Soong Mei-ling"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) With Alexis Carrel, this man authored “The Culture of Organs,” outlining the creation of an artificial heart. This man, at a dinner hosted by Hugh Wilson, controversially accepted the (20 pts)",
        "Order of the German Eagle from Hermann Goring. A speech by this man, given on behalf of (10 pts)",
        "America First, claimed that the Roosevelt administration was a war agitator. The Orteig Prize was won by, for ten points, what pilot of the Spirit of St. Louis, an aviator who made the first nonstop solo flight across the Atlantic?"
      ],
      "answer": "Charles Lindbergh"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Reuters journalist John Rettie broke censorship laws in order to export news of this speech. A “Testament” is quoted by this speech’s orator in a passage claiming that the central figure’s rudeness was “a (20 pts)",
        "defect which cannot be tolerated in one holding the position of General Secretary.” This speech, which was given to the 20th Congress in (10 pts)",
        "1956, contributed to its deliverer’s namesake “thaw” during the Cold War. For ten points, name this speech in which Nikita Khrushchev broke with Stalin’s policies."
      ],
      "answer": "Khrushchev’s Secret Speech or On the Cult of Personality and its Consequences"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Phillips Report, which detailed cost overruns for this project, was revealed to the public by Walter Mondale. Edward White, Roger (20 pts)",
        "Chaffee, and Gus Grissom died during an early phase of this program, which succeeded programs named (10 pts)",
        "Mercury and Gemini. On July 20, 1969, the Sea of Tranquility was the landing site of one of this project’s modules, the Eagle. For ten points, name this project that sent the first astronauts to the Moon."
      ],
      "answer": "Apollo program"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city’s Vigeland Statue Garden includes odd sites like the “Man Attacked by Babies” statue and the “Wheel of Life” sundial fixture. This city is home to the Kon-tiki museum, honoring explorer (20 pts)",
        "Thor Heyerdahl, who crossed much of the Pacific on the namesake raft. This city, which was known as Christiana until the 20th century, is home to (10 pts)",
        "Akershus Fortress, which was built by King Haakon V. In 1993, Israel and the PLO agreed to a set of peace accords named for, for ten points, what capital city of Norway?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Oslo",
        "Christiana before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In the prelude to this conflict, Lord Dalhousie flared tensions by annexing land under the Doctrine of Lapse. Soldiers in this conflict were shot out of cannons during particularly vicious fighting at (20 pts)",
        "Cawnpore. Lucknow was besieged at the start of this conflict. This conflict was sparked after new (10 pts)",
        "cartridges for the Enfield rifle were allegedly greased with fat to offend both Muslim and Hindus soldiers. The British Raj was established in the aftermath of, for ten points, what 1857 revolt in India?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Sepoy Mutiny",
        "Indian Revolt of 1857 before “India” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This treaty led to a controversy over whether Mecklenburg had to concede more than the city of Wismar. A peace that this treaty failed to ensure was finally brokered in the Peace of Pyrenees. Swiss independence from the (20 pts)",
        "Holy Roman Empire was formally established by this treaty, which also led the Dutch Republic to be formally recognized by (10 pts)",
        "Spain and reaffirmed the principles of the Peace of Augsburg. For ten points, name this treaty that was signed in Osnabruck and Munster and ended the Thirty Years War."
      ],
      "answer": "Peace of Westphalia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Campesinos use a Paraguayan version of this instrument to play pieces like “Parajo Campana” [pa-RA-ho cam-PAN-uh]. In traditional Gaelic society, each clan would have a player of this instrument write eulogies for its chiefs. Trinity College houses a medieval (20 pts)",
        "Celtic version of this instrument called the cl´airseach [clar-shock]. Modern versions of this instrument have a six-and-a-half octave range, seven (10 pts)",
        "pedals, and usually 47 strings. For ten points, name this plucked instrument that developed out of the earlier, much smaller lyre."
      ],
      "answer": "Pedal harp"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A division in this battle was positioned to cut off Confederate routes to Bethel Station. Nathan Bedford Forrest nearly died after ordering an attack through fallen timber in this battle. Future President James (20 pts)",
        "Garfield fought on the second and final day of this battle under Don Carlos Buell. A line known as the Sunken Road was established around the key defensive position for the Union, which was called the (10 pts)",
        "Hornet’s Nest. Cutting off the Memphis and Charleston Railroad was a central goal of, for ten points, what April 1862 Civil War battle in Tennessee?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Shiloh",
        "Battle of Pittsburg Landing"
      ]
    }
  ]
}